<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doc>
  
  <node>
    <marker>fred + ginger / read space</marker>
    <text></text>
  </node>
  
  <node>
    <marker>the beginning</marker>
    <text>I appear at the edge of the stage as the last few audience members take their seats. My behavior is matter-of-fact. I have a lot of choices to make in advance of my entrance. I decide on my entrance site and the direction I will travel in relation to the audience, plus where that path will end. Then the light fades.</text>
  </node>
  
  <node>
    <marker>curved path</marker>
    <text>The moment the light returns I step onto the stage, walking in a stride and style not mine, as foreign as a foreign accent, recognizable but odd. The path is a singular broad curve that ends in a slightly accelerated little curl, leaving me facing the portal through which I stepped onto the stage. <n>Nothing about my performance ends at the end of the curl.</n></text>
  </node>
  
  <node>
    <marker>link to portal</marker>
    <text>I am held by an imagined cord linking me to the portal. <n>I attend to the exactness of the single broad curve so that when I face my entrance site it is as if I complete the stringing of an archer’s bow.</n> <n>deliberately create this space within a space, separating me from the audience.</n> An ancient voice quietly advises me to remember the audience as well as the space beyond my tightly contained space. <n>The ancient voice is me from 10,000 years ago bringing that possibility into the present.</n> <n>My choice to perform this material requires catastrophic acts of perception. I associate catastrophic with images of great loss. The magnitude and reoccurrence of choreographed behavior that I need to first recognize and then dis-attach from, again and again, is a personal loss of tremendous proportion.</n></text>
  </node>
  
  <node>
    <marker>break cord and second beginning</marker>
    <text>In response to the guidance received, I select the right moment to break the string and notice at once how the inclusion of the theater and my audience enlarges my dancing. It is like a real opening, and I begin again.</text>
  </node>
  
  <node>
    <marker>joy + sorrow</marker>
    <text>My body is still while joy and sorrow wash across my face like a stream of instances. When not streaming, my face may briefly return to normalcy, or it may sustain a single reflection of joy/sorrow for longer moments. <n>I am not limited to my personal experience of joy and sorrow. It is a relief to know that it is in and about the audience, this theater, and the world beyond its doors.</n> <n>As I perform, I try to remove my tendency to embody the images I use to describe the movement material.</n></text>
  </node>
  
  <node>
    <marker>wordless song</marker>
    <text>I sing a wordless song that arises from and combines joy and sorrow into a single melody that resonates through my bones. Barely suppressing a sense of personal history, my face reflects the transience of joy and sorrow. <n>I hear the song as my voice leaves my body. I am intentionally unguarded because I rarely allow myself to partake in unprotected experiences.</n> <n>I am not translating the written language into movement, i.e., joy and sorrow. I actually aspire toward a bodily speechlessness by noticing my visual field, which includes what I can and cannot see, as well as minute associative instances that rise spontaneously.</n> <n>I understand that joy and sorrow are always present. I do not have to instigate them.</n> The song’s duration is determined by how much time is required for the song to impress itself on my body and the audience’s memory. Its phrasing can expand and contract. <n>Singing a song of joy and sorrow is a challengingly simple way for me to engage my perception of space and time.</n> I attach rhythmic movement to the song, my dancing obviously influenced by my singing. I establish this continuity of relationship before using it to navigate a slightly complex path to the edge of the stage. <n>I strongly maintain the role of the choreographer, overseeing the particularity of the path I travel and making spatial choices without becoming too artistic.</n> Partway, my audible singing disappears, yet the dancing adheres to its reliance on the now unheard rhythm of the song.</text>
  </node>
  
  <node>
    <marker>hidden diagonal</marker>
    <text>And finally my dance shifts outside of the prevailing memory of the song, and I move across stage in a straight line while erasing my destination. <n>While dancing I make an effort not to hesitate. Learned behavior suggests I slow down or listen more in order to get things right. That is a belief that limits my dance.</n></text>
  </node>
  
  <node>
    <marker>1 minute turn</marker>
    <text>At the edge of the stage, with a 1-minute allotment to turn in place a single time without moving slowly or continuously, I perform the joy and sorrow in restraint and sing snippets of the joy/sorrow song on 2 or 3 occasions during the turn. <n>My head is free to look down or away or to turn. It is not fixed.</n></text>
  </node>
  
  <node>
    <marker>work</marker>
    <text>If the sparsely singing turn is like a lock unlocking, then <em>work</em> is my deliverance into space after 1 minute. <n>I accept any movement that arises spontaneously and call it <em>work</em>.</n> Work is a variation on a 2-part spontaneous movement used to cross stage one time. Work is also how I manage the choreographic tools I need to maintain both my interest and that of the audience. Those tools are the perception of my movement as music, my perception of space, the use of stillness and duration, and the perception of joy and sorrow to deepen my practice of performance. <n>During this movement it is helpful to enlarge my perception of space beyond the theater.</n> <n>There is no repetition in live performance.</n> <n><em>Work</em> comes easily. Maybe it is because of what is required to survive as a dancer in contemporary western culture. It can be difficult to dis-attach from the habitual physical response to what “work” looks like, i.e., striving, reaching, pushing, dragging, busying, flailing, hauling.</n> <n>I neither hurry nor linger.</n></text>
  </node>
  
  <node>
    <marker>complexity</marker>
    <text>Complexity arises. I play with how I perceive time and how I perceive space rather than creating complex body movement. Clearing the dance of complexity is as abstruse, yet here I am, two alternating occurrences weaving back and forth. The duration of the two parts is choreographically challenging. <n>The movement is not difficult just because I use the words <em>complexity</em>, havoc, abstruse, choreographically challenging. And <em>clearing the dance of complexity</em> does not necessarily require flowing movement.</n> <n>If I can manage my perception of time and space to inform my body, then I do not have to think about what movement to do next. What I mean by my perception of time is that it is passing. And what I mean by my perception of space is that I include it in my dancing so that I am not seduced by the intelligence, past experiences, patterns, limitations, and/or sensuality of my moving body.</n></text>
  </node>
  
  <node>
    <marker>mall + object</marker>
    <text>I perform market, a contemporary market, <em>a mall</em>. Without creating <em>a mall</em> I notice it wherever I am. <n>I attend to my perception of space and time in order to distract myself from predetermining the outcome of this choreographic direction. It is an effort to refrain from creating a literal mall. Instead, copious instances of <em>a mall</em> appear and disappear as I dance.</n> A single object reveals itself in a mall. I perform several views of object for the benefit of the audience. A mall and object alternate their appearances. <n>I do not create object. I learn its attributes from my body and actually take pleasure in identifying the <em>object</em> for myself in each performance.</n> <n>I remember to notice that my whole body is producing unimaginable instances of specificity.</n></text>
  </node>
  
  <node>
    <marker>particle</marker>
    <text>I start spinning, not literally but as a part of an onstage counterclockwise spinning vortex that only I perceive. I am a speck, a dot, a flake, endlessly spiraling toward center stage, and absolutely no one can possibly identify me as such. <n>The movement may change, but the choreography itself does not change.</n></text>
  </node>
  
  <node>
    <marker>holy + indian</marker>
    <text>At center stage I reverse direction and turn in place while lifting my arms incrementally, to signify the construction and architecture of a holy site. At the same time my shoes lightly tap the floor under me as if to imply the sporadic thwacks of a hammer, striking in the distance. <n>I am <em>a holy site</em> and to perform as such requires the catastrophic loss of how I otherwise perceive myself.</n> <em>A holy site</em> is completed the moment my hands or fingers touch overhead. I open my mouth and hear <em>a holy song</em> rise up out of me. <n>I call what I hear a holy song and notice the feedback from my whole body as it yields to that direction.</n> Unable to sustain itself, <em>a holy site</em> collapses. My hands, still touching, drop before my eyes. I contemplate the symbolism of the gestural demise. Resourcing whatever bits of prior exposure to the American Indian ritual, I reproduce it as best as I can while rhythmlessly bouncing to beating drums that only I can hear. The American Indian ritual collapses. I rebuild a holy site, using the sound of my tapping feet as before. I travel in fading light.</text>
  </node>
  
  <node>
    <marker>tiptoeing</marker>
    <text>Light returns and I am tiptoeing, not wanting to disrupt the space already created – a task I hold in high regard. I experience space parting, with little to no disturbance, hoping that the audience will see this too, before arriving somewhere that is not center stage. My actions are obvious. When I imagine the stage is still, instantaneously perform my almost non-existent fake American Indian ritual dance which I may be the only person in the world to realize. Punctuated by beating drums that only I can hear I may bounce rhythmlessly with the supposed drums.</text>
  </node>
  
  <node>
    <marker>beckett quote</marker>
    <text>I lift and point my right index finger in the air and, speaking in a Southern accent, say, “Strictly speaking I believe I have never been anywhere.” With my finger still in the air, I leave time for the Beckett quote to sink in. <n>The quote’s impact on my body is mind-boggling.</n> <n>My finger can be a trap. I do not fixate on it – deliberately hiding its function in determining my movement.</n></text>
  </node>
  
  <node>
    <marker>silly song and dance</marker>
    <text>My right hand lowers as I hum  “The Snake Charmer’s Song.” My perception of joy and sorrow guides the singing. The lifetime of the song is how long it takes for my hand to lower. My standard for “lower” is my own.</text>
  </node>
  
  <node>
    <marker>market + traditional object</marker>
    <text>I am unquantifiable instances of a <em>5,000-year-old marketplace</em> before sunrise, while it is still dark and quiet. I depend on the image at first, and then I get rid of it. This is not a narrative. Maybe a wind moves the air around a makeshift pole, flap, cover, knot, uneven surface. My hand occasionally thrums my body for sound, or I make short intermittent sounds that are barely audible. <n>It is an effort to refrain from creating a marketplace. Instead, copious instances of predawn marketplace live and die spontaneously. It is all I need.</n> It is the same for a single item, like a particular utensil, crafted tool, or ornament – an untraditional object in a <em>5,000-year-old marketplace</em>. There is no name for the item, fortunately. I provide several views of an untraditional object for the audience. <n>I am not translating the written language into movement, i.e., utensil, crafted tool, marketplace. I actually aspire toward a bodily speechlessness so that I can notice and appreciate the abundance of materiality that can surface momentarily.</n></text>
  </node>
  
  <node>
    <marker>counterintuitive travel</marker>
    <text>I perform counterintuitive travel somewhere at the edge of the space. A cranky voice provides continuous accompaniment. <n>The term “counterintuitive travel” is what it is – another way. Counterintuitive reflects possibility, not intention, psychology, or effort.</n> <n>I do not become cranky. Cranky describes my voice.</n></text>
  </node>
  
  <node>
    <marker>mend</marker>
    <text>I <em>mend</em> the field. <n>Accepting any movement, I call it mend. At the same time it is an effort not to automatically produce comforting arm or hand movements or behave like a mother hen.</n></text>
  </node>
  
  <node>
    <marker>road</marker>
    <text>I build a road with my feet used to smooth and design its surface. My work is clear and evident, without rest. I make a rhythmic sound, like an engine, to create a counterpart to the work of building the road. My arms, held out from my body, symbolize the shape of the engine. <n>I strongly maintain the role of the choreographer, overseeing the design element of the road. I think of the road’s surface as a mosaic, without getting too artistic.</n></text>
  </node>
  
  <node>
    <marker>holy site + song</marker>
    <text>I turn and turn and turn, as many times as I remain interested in turning on this big new road, bringing separate parts together in a whirling whole that becomes <em>a holy site</em> somewhere on stage. The turning is happening in my perception of the whole stage, and my body is just a part of it. My arms are above my head, and they function as the architecture of the temple, shrine, church, mosque, etc. My hands, like antenna, draw <em>a holy song</em> down through <em>a holy site</em> and out through my mouth. It does not have to be anything other than holy – holy being different for everyone. My arms collapse, poised like a mound of rubble in front of me. Holding my body still, I step toward the audience to offer them several views of the former holy site. I rebuild the road, as before. At center stage, my arms again lift above my head to symbolize the architecture of a holy site, and a holy song returns. A second abrupt fall destroys the holy site, turning it back into rubble. My ancient self’s voice guides me back to a standing position. Everything seems in order.</text>
  </node>
  
  <node>
    <marker>standing</marker>
    <text>I am standing straight, except that I am facing away from the audience.</text>
  </node>
  
  <node>
    <marker>face audience</marker>
    <text>The final encouragement I receive from my ancient self has me turn to face the audience once more. Pause.</text>
  </node>
  
  <node>
    <marker>joy + sorrow again</marker>
    <text>When my face begins streaming with joy and sorrow, I begin anew.</text>
  </node>

  <node>
    <marker>end</marker>
    <text></text>
  </node>
  
</doc>